Good morning and פורים שמח. Purim Sameach. So today’s דף Daf is
קמ״ד, Kuf Mem Daled, and we pick up on the bottom of
קמ״ד Kuf Mem Daled עמוד א׳, Amud Alef, which was אשכחן רבי
יהודה, Ashkhachan Rabbi Yehuda, three lines from the bottom. So just to
summarize,
the משנה Mishnah talks about a barrel that breaks on שבת Shabbos
and saving wine from the barrel, which somewhat echoes earlier discussions about
saving things that are going to burn down, although there by saving
that they were going to burn down there were issues about permitting
things that might have been somewhat אסור דרבנן assur d’rabbanan because of
a concern that if you didn’t come to do it, the person
would come to put out the fire. Here it's hard to understand
what the problem was at all in terms of saving issues, you
know, oil or wine that comes out of the barrel, but there's
concerns about that it’s too much טרחא tircha or עובדא דחול uvda
d’chol and so on. Anyway, from there the משנה Mishnah moves on
to a more central concern, which is the issue about squeezing, which
we also had at the end of the last פרק, perek, and
that is that you should not use a sponge to get the
oil because you’ll come to squeeze it out, and then issues about
fruit juices, about oil and wine that come out of grapes or
other types of fruit, and whether you can benefit from them on
שבת Shabbos or are we concerned that if we allow you to
benefit from them you’ll come to squeeze them. And there there was
a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים, Chachamim, where
the חכמים Chachamim say that, it seems like in all cases you’re
not allowed to benefit from them, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
if the fruit was set aside for food you’re allowed to benefit
from the juices that come out. Here's a simple example: right, let’s
say you have grapefruits, and you’re eating grapefruits on שבת Shabbos and
some of the juice comes out as you’re eating it, are you
allowed to drink from it? So it was set aside for food,
are you allowed to benefit or to drink from the juice that
comes out? And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said yes, because it was
set aside for food we’re not afraid you’ll come to squeeze from
it. Now the גמרא Gemara distinguishes between the types of fruit. The
גמרא Gemara says basically divides three categories: זיתים וענבים, zeitim va’anavim,
olives and grapes, which it says there’s a debate whether רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would allow even that when the juices came out by
themselves set aside for food, but at least the position the גמרא
Gemara is working with now is that no, in that case רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would concede to the rabbis that even if you
set it aside for food you cannot benefit from what comes out.
Then you have in the middle category, תותים ורימונים, tusim v'rimonim, pomegranates
and strawberries, which presumably are somewhat more frequently squeezed, but not as
much as grapes and olives, and those, that’s the area where they
debate. And then you have שאר פירות, shear perot, all other types
of things, which are very rare that they would be squeezed, and
there even if the juices came out,
even the rabbis would say that it is not a problem. Okay,
now on the one hand I’ll just make one mention and this
is going to be important for the rest of today’s דף. daf.
What is the difference between those three categories? The easiest thing to
say is it's just a question of frequency. You know, everybody always
squeezes olives and grapes, sometimes you squeeze a pomegranate, and the other
things is very rare. So the likelihood you’ll come to squeeze is
different in those three cases, and the two extremes are agreed upon
and the debate is the middle case. However, it is important to
point out that olives and grapes have a different story as well,
which is not just the likelihood but the fact that the liquids
that come from olives and grapes is, what is it? What liquid
comes from olives and grapes? Olive oil and wine, which are classic
liquids, right, for us and certainly in the ancient world, these were
like the prime liquids, and every other liquid had no significance. You
know, these, if you ask people what were the most important liquids
in your life, they'd say basically water, olive oil and wine. Okay,
so the point could be that it’s not just that it’s common,
but that הלכתית halachically the what’s produced from that is something that
is has is recognized הלכה halacha as something of meaning. It has
a שם משקה, shem mashkeh, it's actually called a liquid. Okay, if
you think about it there’s seven liquids that, you know, cause for
טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Anyway, olive oil and wine are among them.
So what we will distinguish is that the idea that those two
are the ones which are probably the only ones that דאורייתא d'oraisa
biblically you would transgress if you actually squeezed the grapes and olives.
Because if you squeeze an orange and got orange juice, even if
it was common to do it, even if it was not like
a שינוי shinui or דרך, derech, it was common to do it,
nevertheless the orange juice would be considered like, you know, just like
waste product essentially. So you’re weird, you want to drink it. Well,
even if it's somewhat common, it doesn’t have significance and therefore it's
not like you did an act of really producing a משקה. mashkeh.
So that could also be why the case of olives and grapes
is agreed upon, not just because it’s a big concern you’ll come
to squeeze it, but also because, as we’ll see, that’s the case
that definitely is a דאורייתא d'oraisa and again, not just because it’s
common, but because of what it produces.
Okay, so first of all does that change the מינה? mina?
Right, but that’s why I pointed out: if it was a question
of just how common, then those categories might change. But if it’s
a question about the status of olive oil and wine, then at
least the דאורייתא d'oraisa category doesn’t change. The other issues might be
a question of how degree of how common they are. But the
olive oil and wine is the דאורייתא d'oraisa specifically because of the
status of those two. So anyway, that’s why there’s the debate of
those three categories about using the liquid, but it also will translate
into questions of... of when are you actually allowed or you know
how bad is it to actually squeeze the stuff itself. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues, so yesterday the גמרא Gemara had tried to
demonstrate or demonstrated that that Rabbi Yehuda agreed to the Rabbis by
olives and grapes, and that one extreme, and now we're going to
look at the other extreme. So three lines from the bottom, אשכחן
רבי יהודה דמודי לרבנן בזיתים וענבים. Ashkechan Rabbi Yehuda d'modei l'Rabanan b'zeisim
va'anavim. So we found yesterday that Rabbi Yehuda agrees to the Rabbis
with olives and grapes that those there is a concern that you
can't benefit from the juices that run off because we're afraid you'll
come to squeeze even when it's set aside for food, there's a
high concern that you'll come to squeeze. And as I just said,
it would be the דאורייתא D'Oraisa if you would come to
squeeze. רבנן דמודי ליה לרבי יהודה בשאר פירות מנלן? Rabanan d'modei lei
l'Rabbi Yehuda b'sha'ar peiros minalan? How do we know the Rabbis agree
to Rabbi Yehuda that if the juices come out of other fruits
that are not זיתים וענבים, zeisim va'anavim, excuse me, that are not
תותים ורימונים, tutim v'rimonim, that are not
strawberries and pomegranates, the stuff that's very rare to be squeezed, how
do we know that they say, yeah, that type of juice, no
problem, you can benefit from if it comes off by itself? דתניא,
Detanya, as it's taught in a
ברייתא, Baraisa,
סוחטין בפגין
ובפרישין ובאוגרדין. sochtin b'fagin u'v'prishin u'v'ozradin. You can go ahead and you
can squeeze. Now פגין, pagin, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, are
prunes. Okay, prunes. Okay, פרישין prishin are
רש"י Rashi says, an oh קווידנס kvydons which I don't know is
quince, right? And אוגרדין ozradin are I believe are crab apples. I
have no idea what quince is, quince is quince. Okay, so anyway,
yes, so what? what was your question back there? Okay, alright. So
anyway, you can squeeze these things. Okay, so, so you can actually
squeeze לכתחילה. lechatchila. Okay,
you're ממש מותר mamash mutar to do it because it's in a
category that is very uncommon. Certainly it's not זיתים וענבים, zeisim va'anavim,
but even that, it's a category that's very uncommon, you're even allowed
to do it לכתחילה, lechatchila, there's no even an איסור דרבנן issur
d'rabbanan to squeeze from them on שבת. Shabbos. אבל לא ברימונים, Aval
lo b'rimonim, but not pomegranates. של בית מנשיא בן מנחם היו סוחטין
רימונים. Shel beis Menashia ben Menachem hayu sochtin rimonim. And just to
show you that pomegranates is not so crazy, is not so weird,
and therefore that's why it's at least אסור דרבנן, assur d'rabbanan, is
because we know that in the house of Menashia they used to
do that, they would produce pomegranate juice. So therefore that's why it's
in this middle category. So by the way, this is talking about
the לכתחילה lechatchila question, not the fruit juices, but are you allowed
to do the act of squeezing? And here we say that there
are these levels, and this is as I said, this is how
we basically rule the הלכה. halacha. זיתים וענבים Zeisim va'anavim is דאורייתא,
D'Oraisa, רימונים rimonim and תותים tutim is דרבנן, d'rabbanan, and things that
are very rare and uncommon is even completely מותר. mutar. Now I'm
going to discuss the last two categories and where to draw the
line in a minute, but that's basically the point of this ברייתא
Baraisa to say there's a category of מותר mutar and there's a
category of at least אסור assur presumably דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Now let's first
read. וממאי דרבנן היא? U'mimai d'Rabanan hi? Who told you that's the
Rabbis? When it says you're allowed to do it, you're trying to
say the Rabbis agree you're allowed to do other fruit, we don't
worry about the fruit juices. Who says that's the Rabbis? דילמא רבי
יהודה היא? Dilma Rabbi Yehuda hi? Maybe it's Rabbi Yehuda who in
general is more lenient, maybe he's the one that's allowing you to
squeeze those prunes? So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, big deal, ותהא
נמי רבי יהודה. u'seha nami Rabbi Yehuda. Fine, let it be Rabbi
Yehuda, but it's still telling you something we didn't know before. אימור
דשמעת ליה לרבי יהודה יצאו מעצמן. Eimur d'shamas lei l'Rabbi Yehuda yatz'u
me'atzman. When did Rabbi Yehuda say you can benefit, you know, it's
not a problem when the juices run off by
themselves? סוחטין לכתחילה מי שמעת ליה? Sochtin lechatchila mi shamas lei? He
never heard him say explicitly that you could squeeze things לכתחילה lechatchila
on שבת. Shabbos. אלא מאי אית לך למימר? Ela mai is lach
l'meimar? What do you have to say based on this ברייתא Baraisa
that you're allowing to squeeze it לכתחילה? lechatchila? כיון דלאו בני סחיטה
נינהו, Keivan d'lav b'nei sechita ninhu, since things that are not even
like pomegranates, things that are like no normal person squeezes, אפילו לכתחילה,
afilu lechatchila, so Rabbi Yehuda would allow you to do it לכתחילה.
lechatchila. So here's the point, the point is until now Rabbi Yehuda
and the Rabbis presumably only argued in terms of how much of
a safeguard to make on a concern what you might come to
do. They never disagreed on the acts that were actually forbidden or
permissible on שבת, Shabbos, right? It's only a question about are we
concerned what it will lead to. Here we're finding out that things
that are not normally squeezed, there's no problem to squeeze. Let's say
it's according to Rabbi Yehuda, it should be true according to the
Rabbis because we never debated the act of
squeezing. So ותהא אפילו תימא רבנן, u'seha afilu teima Rabanan, and even
the Rabbis should agree to that. כיון דלאו בני סחיטה נינהו, Keivan
d'lav b'nei sechita ninhu, since this category is not considered you know
things that are not squeezed at all, אפילו לכתחילה, afilu lechatchila, it
should even be permissible לכתחילה. lechatchila. שמע מינה רבנן היא. Shema mina
Rabanan hi. You see it's the Rabbis, it's even the Rabbis. שמע
מינה. Shema mina. It's a good proof. Which is pretty amazing they
only proved it just based on like you know like like by
the rational argument which is you know okay but logical argument, not
based on a text. And maybe you could have said maybe the
reason the Rabbis and Rabbi Yehuda debate about this גזירה gezeirah is
because they debate what actually is the דאורייתא, D'Oraisa, you know what
actually how אסור assur it is to do the thing itself. But
the גמרא Gemara says no, the גמרא Gemara is convinced that because
this is an issue here of this is מותר לכתחילה, mutar lechatchila,
everybody should agree it's מותר לכתחילה. mutar lechatchila. These are things that
are not squeezed at all. Now the interesting question becomes for us,
what is in that category? Because what's the דאורייתא, D'Oraisa, we're pretty
confident to say that's זיתים וענבים. zeisim va'anavim. That clearly is it
and maybe only that. Like you could raise nowadays there are certainly
certain strands of fruit that are that are grown specifically to be
made into juice. Not just that we drink a lot of apple
juice, but there are types of apples or there are types of
oranges, like Valencia oranges, right, are made specifically for the purpose of
creating juice. Okay. So you could say that type of an orange
is completely דאורייתא D'oraisa because that's primarily what it's for. Nevertheless, so
some might say it's דאורייתא, D'oraisa, but many will still say, I'm
sorry, it's still דרבנן. D'rabanan. The only thing that's דאורייתא D'oraisa is
something that produces olive oil or or wine, only those classic משקים
Mashkim are דאורייתא. D'oraisa. But there might be some things that some
people will argue is דאורייתא. D'oraisa. The more interesting category is what's
דרבנן D'rabanan versus what is מותר. Mutar. Okay, because this גמרא Gemara
and we're going to see in a minute will try to define
what are the parameters of this בית מנשה. Beis Menashe. How many
people have to be in the בית מנשה Beis Menashe category to
make something enough the normal way to do it that it's אסור
דרבנן? Assur D'rabanan? And nowadays in particular where, you know, we have
a lot of imported fruit, so a lot of things get, you
know, turned into fruit in different places. What exactly is the story?
We'll read a little bit more of the גמרא Gemara and then
I'll talk about להלכה L'halacha what exactly is the line between דרבנן
D'rabanan and מותר. Mutar. Yes. Two things.
The interesting corollary then would be like, you know, these days your
average householder isn't squeezing grapes for grape juice. Like if I just
took my eating grapes and I squeezed them...
You mean in terms of the איסור דרבנן Issur D'rabanan that you'll
come to do it? You mean it might still be a דאורייתא
D'oraisa because it's done commercially, but how much should we be גוזר
דרבנן Gozer D'rabanan you'll come to do it if you don't do
it around the house? That's your point?
No, more even or is it דאורייתא D'oraisa only
like...
my main question was...
That would be דאורייתא D'oraisa if it's done commercially and these are,
you know, this is what it's, you know, it's... The דאורייתא D'oraisa
doesn't... that... the דאורייתא D'oraisa doesn't change anyway because it's olive oil
and and wine. But even the דרבנן D'rabanan presumably doesn't change if
it's normally done commercially even though though it's not done personally, presumably.
Although I hear your point, you could make that argument if no...
but nevertheless that's not... I mean, it's an interesting point. I haven't
seen anybody do this, but the assumption normally is is that that
doesn't change the question of the act of squeezing itself. The interesting
question is maybe that should change the איסור Issur about benefiting from
the fruit because the concern that what you'll come to do might
be different if no householder normally does it and it's only done
commercially. But anyway, in general we seem to apply these categories straight
regardless of your point.
The different question also was... But we have all these other questions
like, you know, like squeezing a towel. So I guess that's common?
You know, we don't go swim because maybe you'll take a towel
and then come to squeeze it.
Yeah, it is pretty common. It is pretty common that you're carrying
a wet towel, you come to squeeze it out, or you might
or you might incidentally squeeze it out. Now the question that you
really want to ask is that, you know, why is it a
problem squeezing a towel if it's not a problem about squeezing certain
juice... you know, certain fruit? Okay, so we'll get back... Fine. Okay,
no, the question was what you'll come to do... No, the question
is why is it at all a problem? Okay, why isn't it
just like other fruit? Okay, fine, I'll get back to that in
a minute. Yes, Charlie.
I was going to say even grapes there are different... you don't
get grape juice or wine from table grapes. Right.
That was my question.
Ah,
so it's like cases that grapes which are... No, your question is
that it's done at a commercial level. His question is that these
types of grapes... Okay, these types of grapes, what they produce aren't
even like classic grape juice or... That's an interesting question.
Most people generally will not pop Concord grapes in their mouth because
they have seeds. Right.
Right. That's an interesting question. Well there are seedless... a lot of
people eat seedless grapes, but that's an interesting question. If it's a
type of grape that is not made for that and and doesn't
produce that as a good quality, that type of stuff, maybe that
wouldn't be a דאורייתא. D'oraisa. Exactly. That's a good question. So maybe
everything's going to converge on the דרבנן. D'rabanan. Could be. Okay, so
let's talk now about the line between the דרבנן D'rabanan and what's
מותר. Mutar. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ושבי מנשה בר
מנחם היו סוחטים ברימונים. U'shvei Menashe Bar Menachem Hayu Sochtim B'rimonim. And
this is why it's at least אסור דרבנן Assur D'rabanan because they
would do it in this house of מנשה בר מנחם. Menashe Bar
Menachem. So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, so said רב נחמן,
Rav Nachman, הלכה כשבי מנשה בר מנחם. Halacha K'shvei Menashe Bar Menachem.
We rule like שבי מנשה בר מנחם. Shvei Menashe Bar Menachem. So
אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar Lei Rava L'Rav Nachman, מנשה בר
מנחם תנא הוא? Menashe Bar Menachem Tana Hu?
What do you mean we rule like him? He's a he's a
pomegranate juice producer, he's not a תנא. Tana. So
there, very appropriate for פורים. Purim. He wasn't giving a הלכה Halacha
ruling, they just made pomegranate juice. So anyway, תנא הוא? Tana Hu?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, וכי תימא הלכה כהאי תנא דסבר
לה כשבי מנשה בר מנחם. Vechi Seima Halacha Kehai Tana D'savar Lah
K'shvei Menashe Bar Menachem. No, what he meant to say was we
rule like the author of the ברייתא Braisa who made reference to
מנשה בר מנחם, Menashe Bar Menachem, who was concerned with that phenomenon
and said because of that phenomenon it's אסור Assur to squeeze. So
okay, it's pretty clear that's what he meant, but it was a
cute little retort. So the point is we rule that pomegranate juice
is a problem because of this phenomenon that people would squeeze it.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ומשום דסבר כמנשה בר מנחם הלכה כמותו?
U'mishum D'savar K'menashe Bar Menachem
Halacha K'moso? What,
just because he holds like... which just means just because he's concerned
with just or just because of this phenomenon
מנשה בר מנחם's Menashe Bar Menachem like pomegranate juice factory, therefore we
we have to, you know, rule that way? One minute. מנשה בר
מנחם הוי רובא דעלמא? Menashe Bar Menachem Havei Ruba D'alma? What, is
he the majority of the world? One weird guy makes pomegranate juice,
why should that dictate for the rest of us? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אין, In, yes. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה...
Mishna... that sometimes we are concerned by things that occur even like
in a subset, you know, a subgroup of society, or whatever, by
some people, דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה. Mishnah. המקיים קוצים
בכרם. Hamkayem kotzim bekerem.
Somebody that allows like thornbushes in his vineyard. Is that so, is
that a type of a כלאים kilayim because thornbushes normally isn't like
a type of a thing that's grown for food? So רבי אליעזר
אומר קדש, Rabbi Eliezer omer kadesh, you have sanctified, which is a
way phrase of meaning you've made it into כלאים. kilayim. וחכמים אומרים
אינו מקדש, Vachachamim omrim eino mekadesh, it does not make it into
כלאים. kilayim. אלא דבר שכמותו מקיימין, Ela davar shekemoto mekaymin, only things
that normally normal people keep around because they're growing it for, you
know, for food. Not something like this that normal people rip out.
ואמר רבי חנינא, Ve'amar Rabbi Chanina, קוצי שדות בגמליהם, kotzei sadot begmaleihem,
I'm sorry I skipped a line. ואמר רבי
חנינא, Ve'amar Rabbi Chanina, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? mai ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer?
What's the reason that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's a problem?
He doesn't just disagree with the principle. שבכן בערביא מקיימין קוצי שדות
לגמליהם Shebechein be'arvaya mekaymin kotzei sadot legmaleihem because in Arabia they keep
these thornbushes, they grow them in order to feed to their camels.
So you see that because in some place this is something that
is done, it makes a problem even in your place, even if
it's not done. So the same should be true with this pomegranate.
Speaking of non-human consumption
presumably, yes, but that's not our issue, but yes. So the גמרא
Gemara says, מידי איריא? midi irya? What? Is that relevant?
דערביא אתרא, de'arvaya atra, Arabia is a whole location, it's a country,
it's a geographic area where it's very common in that area. So
because it's well, it's common there, it should imply, it should have
implications of even things outside there. הכא בטלה דעתו אצל כל אדם.
hacha batla da'ato etzel kol adam. Here one person who does it.
You see I've been sort of saying maybe to contemporize it like
he has this pomegranate juice factory, but the גמרא Gemara didn't even
say that. Maybe they just did it privately, right? So then you
certainly understand the question, because if they did it in their factory
and everybody around bought from it, that obviously would make it a
מקום, makom, it would be common in the whole place. But here
you're saying it's one guy who does it, בטלה דעתו אצל כל
אדם, batla da'ato etzel kol adam, it should be completely irrelevant to
everybody else. So before we go on, basically
the, this leads to a discussion about what is אסור דרבנן למעשה.
assur deRabbanan lema'aseh. And the basic first assertion which limits the category
is only the types of things that are like very prevalent in
your geographic region. Exactly how broadly you define your geographic region isn't
so clear, but basically it's not just some thing that a few
people do, it has to be a very common widespread thing in
your geographic
region.
But then becomes an interesting question which is let's say it's not,
let's say it's common in a different geographic region that isn't
yours. Or let's say even to add to that, you import fruit
from that geographic region or fruit juice, so therefore it is common
here not because they do it here but because you import. Or
then they even create hypotheticals. Let's say over in Florida it's a
very common to squeeze oranges for orange juice, and it's not common
here, but the reason it's not common here is because we don't
have oranges. So if we were to in theory it's like you
know the joke like you know, if you were to have a
brother would he like? Anyway, if we were to have oranges would
we squeeze them? And the answer would be yes. So that would
make it considered enough דרך. derech. So based on those types of
concerns of importing and what would we do had this thing been
very commonly grown here, it winds up that
it's extremely broad what's in this category of things that are אסור
דרבנן. assur deRabbanan. Okay, we wind up saying almost everything. You know,
I mean I guess if you had something like prunes, we know
people like prune juice, I guess crabapples, I've never heard anybody make
crabapple juice. So if you could find a type of a thing
that is you know really rare that anybody ever makes juice out
of, that would be מותר. mutar. But basically we, you know, basically
almost everything gets put into the דרבנן deRabbanan category. And you know,
the point that was being made here about like even grapes or
sometimes you know are not the grapes used for grape juice and
so on, maybe you could start putting them into the דרבנן deRabbanan
category. But basically להלכה lehalacha we assume grapes and olives are דאורייתא
de'oraita and pretty much everything else is דרבנן. deRabbanan. We put very
little, very few things into this category of מותר. mutar. I will
tell you though there's an interesting בית יוסף Beit Yosef which translates
into the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch which is he says that it
was very common to squeeze lemons on שבת. Shabbos. And not lemons
onto fish, that's squeezing into food which we'll get to, which is
מותר. mutar. But סתם stam squeeze lemons into I don't know tea
or make lemonade, and he says how is that possible? Like people
produce all this lemon juice commercially, how can it be מותר? mutar?
And he like stands on his head to try to figure out
why it could be מותר. mutar. One, he tries to make an
argument maybe it's not so common to make, to squeeze lemons to
make lemon juice, which is really a hard argument. Anyway the best
argument he can come up with, what? It's all used for. I
know, I know. So the best argument he can come up with
is that nobody ever drinks the lemon juice straight. You only drink
it with mixing so you never drink it to be a משקה
mashke in itself. But anyway, but so because that was a very
common phenomenon he tries to find a way to say it was
מותר, mutar, but in practice we pretty much say that almost every
fruit unless something. is really rare, is in the אסור דרבנן assur
d'rabbanan category. Okay, now to make one comment about the question that
was raised before about why we're so concerned the other day about
squeezing water out of things.
So squeezing water that's absorbed into fabric is two possible concerns. One
is ליבון, libun, that you're actually getting the thing cleaner when you
squeeze something out. There, there's an interesting debate in the ראשונים. rishonim.
Some say it's only ליבון libun when you squeeze out water because
the normal way you laundry is you put things in water and
you wring out the water. Some say it's ליבון libun even other
liquids because if it's a bad liquid, you got wine in it
and you don't want the wine in it and you're squeezing out
the liquid you don't want, that's also part of the cleaning process.
So one there's an issue of ליבון. libun. And the other is
an issue of סחיטה sechitah when you're trying to get out the
thing because you want the liquid that's extracted. Like you're squeezing out
like you absorbed the wine that fell out of the barrel and
then you're going to squeeze it out because you want to you
want to salvage the wine. Okay, so there that is a problem
and there actually
some say that if unless it's absorbed, you know, unless it has
absorbed like wine or oil, if it absorbs other liquids, then it
won't actually be a דאורייתא, d'oraissa, it'll only be a דרבנן d'rabbanan
because you're only squeezing out things that they themselves even if they
were squeezed out from the original like juice or whatever, from the
original fruit would not be a דאורייתא. d'oraissa. There is an interesting
question though that that type of squeezing of of liquids absorbed in
cloth or whatever that's done that's seen as a type of a
מפרק, mefarek, doing it for the sake of the liquid, not for
cleansing, is compared to these issues that we've discussed and some actually
do apply some of the same limits, you know. But our משנה
mishna started with a case of wine, so at least that would
be similar in that regard. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara continues
in the following way.
Can you do ליבון libun if you don't really care? It's not
like you really want your...
Yeah, so there are cases where it's מותר mutar דרך לכלוך derech
lichluch and so on, it's a process of wiping up a spill
so you're getting the thing dirty, you can't call it an act
of ליבון. libun. I'm not talking getting to the point of תכל'ס
הלכה למעשה, tachlis halacha l'maaseh, but yeah, there are parameters where you're
not so concerned about squeezing, okay. Now the גמרא gemara says like
this, אלא היי טעמא. ela hai ta'ama. So the גמרא gemara still
doesn't know why pomegranates are a problem because it says it's a
rare occurrence. So here is the reason, כדרב חסדא? k'rav chisda? What
רב חסדא? rav chisda? דאמר רב חסדא, d'amar rav chisda, רב חסדא
rav chisda says, תרדין שסחטן ונתנן במקוה. tardin she'sechtan u'nesanan b'mikvah. תרדין
tardin are beets, right? Is that beets?
Okay, beets.
You squeeze beets and you put them into a מקוה. mikvah. So
the beet juice, פוסלין את המקוה בשינוי מראה. poslin es ha'mikvah b'shinuy
mareh. They invalidate the מקוה mikvah when it changes the color of
the מקוה. mikvah. The basic הלכה halacha is
is that drawn water, water that doesn't come straight like there's rain
water, invalidates a מקוה mikvah with three לוג. log. Okay, actually it's
three לוג log before the מקוה mikvah is full. Once the מקוה
mikvah has a full forty סאה, se'ah, it's not a problem. Things
that are liquids that are not water invalidate the מקוה mikvah when
they change the color of the מקוה. mikvah. Okay.
Even when there's forty סאה? se'ah?
Even when there's forty סאה se'ah and even if there's less than
three לוג log of this. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara
says, בשינוי מראה והא לאו בני סחיטה נינהו. b'shinuy mareh v'ha lav
bney sechitah ninhu. One minute. Why, says the גמרא, gemara, should beet
juice invalidate the מקוה? mikvah? The מקוה mikvah isn't invalidated just by
the mere fact that it changed colors. If you have just water
and something happened and there was some chemical reaction and now it
looks a weird color, the מקוה mikvah is כשר. kasher. Whatever, yeah,
the מקוה mikvah is כשר, kasher, okay. מקוה mikvah does not become
פסול. pasul. The changing of the color is a measure of the
amount of bad liquid that was that was put into the מקוה.
mikvah. So it has to be a bad liquid that was put
into the מקוה. mikvah. So the גמרא gemara says why is beet
juice considered a liquid? It's not considered a משקה mashkeh at all,
nobody squeezes it, and here's the point I was saying before, it's
not just how common it is, is whether הלכה halacha recognizes the
juice that comes out as a liquid. Does it have a some
status of a liquid or is it just like waste product? Okay.
So the גמרא gemara says why is this considered a liquid? והא
לאו בני סחיטה נינהו. v'ha lav bney sechitah ninhu. You don't normally
squeeze beets to make beet juice. אלא מאי אית לך למימר, ela
mai is lach l'meimar, so what can you say? כיון דאחשבינהו הוו
להו משקה. keivan d'achshavinehu havu lehu mashkeh. Since you gave it significance,
you chose to make beet juice, then you gave it a status
as a משקה. mashkeh. That's enough to give it the status. הכא
נמי, hacha nami, here too, by the תותים ורימונים, tutim u'rimonim, כיון
דאחשבינהו, keivan d'achshavinehu, if you give it significance by squeezing it, הוו
להו משקה, havu lehu mashkeh, you turn it into a משקה. mashkeh.
Now of course if that's true, then the question is why is
it limited to pomegranates? Any you should be allowed to squeeze anything.
So רש"י Rashi tells us both say you're right. According to this
position in the גמרא, gemara, which is not how we פסקן, pasken,
but according to this position in the גמרא, gemara, you can't squeeze
any fruit for its juices because you will by subjectively giving it
significance make it a משקה. mashkeh. And when the משנה mishna allowed
you to squeeze other things, it's only when you're doing it to
get rid of the excess juice. But if you're doing it for
the sake of producing juice, not just to rid it of the
excess juice, according to this stage of the גמרא, gemara, it's always
forbidden because objectively you have made it into a משקה. mashkeh. Okay,
we're not going to stay that way, but that's what the גמרא
gemara is saying. So that's answer number one. That yes, no matter
what the rest of the world does, for you it's a משקה.
mashkeh. רב פפא אמר, Rav Papa amar, no, משום דהוי דבר שאין
עושין ממנו מקוה לכתחלה. mishum d'havi davar she'ein osin mimenu mikvah l'chatchila.
Whoever said you need it something to have a halachic status of
משקה... mashkeh... to invalidate a מקוה. mikveh. It's not true. Even if
we don't call it a משקה, mashkeh, anything you cannot make a
מקוה mikveh out of, וכל דבר שאין עושין ממנו מקוה לכתחילה, vechol
davar she'ein osin mimenu mikveh l'chatchilah, anything that itself is not kosher
for a
מקוה, mikveh, פוסל את המקוה בשינוי מראה, posul es hamikveh b'shinuy mareh,
invalidates the מקוה mikveh when it changes the color. Okay, so therefore
he says basically he disagrees with the premise. You're trying to say,
"Oh, beet juice, but it's not a משקה, mashkeh, it must be
it's defined as a משקה." mashkeh. Who said that to invalidate a
מקוה mikveh you need a משקה? mashkeh? Some type of a thing,
it's enough that physically it's a liquid even if not הלכתית halachically
it has status, and that invalidates a מקוה mikveh when it changes
the color. End of story.
Is it like Tempera powder in it or something?
Well, that's the question. When it says כל דבר שאין עושין ממנו
לכתחילה, kol davar she'ein osin mimenu l'chatchilah, does he mean still it
has to be sort of liquid-like, but it just doesn't need the
הלכתי halachic status of a liquid? Right, let's say you put in
some iron and it caused and the rust caused it to change.
Does he literally mean כל דבר kol davar or does it still
have to be liquid-like? But his so that's not clear, but the
point still is it doesn't have to have a הלכתי halachic status
of משקה mashkeh like some liquid of significance. Right, that's not what's
necessary to invalidate the מקוה. mikveh. Okay, so now we're going to
have a similar debate about מקוה. mikveh. We're going to digress for
מקוה mikveh for a minute about seeing this debate. תנן התם, tnan
hatam, over there: נפל לתוכו יין או חומץ ומוחל, nafal l'tocho yayin
o chometz u'mochal,
let's say into the מקוה mikveh fell wine or vinegar, presumably wine
vinegar, or מוחל mochal which is like the water of that comes
off of olives, not olive oil,
ושינו מראיו, v'shinu mar'av, and it changed the color of the
מקוה, mikveh, פסול, pasul, it's
invalid. So מאן תנא דמוחל משקה הוא? man tanna d'mochal mashkeh hu?
Again, working with the assumption that the only thing that invalidates a
מקוה mikveh is something that has a status of a משקה, mashkeh,
so who's the תנא tanna that considers this olive water a
משקה? mashkeh? אמר אביי: amar Abaye: רבי יעקב היא, Rabbi Yaakov hi,
דתניא: d'tanya: רבי יעקב אומר: Rabbi Yaakov omer: מוחל הרי הוא כמשקה.
mochal harei hu k'mashkeh. Now, this is not for purposes of a
מקוה, mikveh, he's saying this for purposes of becoming טמא. tamei. When
you touch it, it becomes טמא, tamei, only thing that's recognized as
a משקה mashkeh becomes טמא. tamei. Okay, ומה טעם אמרו מוחל היוצא
בתחילה טהור? u'mah tam amru mochal hayotzei betchilah tahor? So why did
they say that the initial juices that came out of an olive
is טהור, tahor, does not become טמא, tamei, if I said that
this מוחל mochal is? לפי שאינו רוצה בקיומו. l'fi she'eino rotzeh b'kiyumo.
Because that's the type of stuff that nobody even bothers keeps, you
just throw out. Again, I don't remember, I should have checked about
the production of olive oil. But the production of olive oil is
not just squeezing olives, right? Somebody mentioned this before that there's this
whole processing that goes through and it's crushing and pressing and that
I know that it's a crushing and a pressing. But anyway, the
juices that come off in this non-processed way are not the same
as the olive oil. But he says that the stuff that comes
out initially, that's not a problem because that everybody just gets rid
of. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, but other מוחל mochal is
an issue. רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: מוחל אינו כמשקה, mochal
eino k'mashkeh, it's not a משקה. mashkeh. ומה טעם אמרו מוחל היוצא
מעיקר בית הבד טמא? u'mah tam amru mochal hayotzei me'ikar beis habad
tamei? But we have the other extreme. On the one hand, everybody
agrees that the juices that come out at the beginning is not
טמא. tamei. On the other hand, after you've actually pressed the olives
and you've extracted the olive oil, if then some juices come out,
whatever, then everybody agrees that it is טמא, tamei, that's עיקר בית
הבד, ikar beis habad, which is like the beam of the pressing
and the press house. Why there do we say it is טמא?
tamei? לפי שלא אפשר שלא בצחצחי שמן. l'fi she'lo efshar she'lo b'tzitzchei
shemen. At that stage, even though it's just water and it's not
olive oil, there're going to be some droplets of olive oil in
it. So it's טמא tamei because of the presence of the olive
oil. So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute,
it's מכשיר machshir things for טומאה? tumah?
Yes,
but also that it can become טמא tamei if you touch it.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, we have the
two extremes that everybody agreed on. What's the case that they disagree
on? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu?
Where do they disagree? Everybody says that the juice that comes out
at the beginning is not a problem and the juice that comes
out at the end everybody says is a problem because either it
itself is considered משקה mashkeh or it has droplets of oil in
it. So where do they ever debate?
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? איכא בינייהו דאתי בתר
אצצטא. ika beinaihu d'asei basar itztatzta. It comes after basically the stuff
has been mounded up and so it's not the juice that comes
out initially, it hasn't been pressed yet, but it's been sitting there
in a big pile and because of the pressure and the weight
or whatever that causes some juice to come out. So it's juice
that would come out, which would not have olive oil mixed into
it, and on the other hand, it's for some reason it's juice
that you don't discard. So there could be a case where you
have this juice that's free from olive oil that's not discarded, that's
the case that they debate. Anyway, what we see is is that
there's a debate whether you consider מוחל mochal to be a הלכתי
halachic liquid. So therefore the idea that מוחל mochal invalidates a מקוה
mikveh would only be either the type of מוחל mochal or the
position that says that מוחל mochal is a liquid. So the גמרא
Gemara says that's אביי's Abaye answer. Assuming that you need a formal
liquid to invalidate a מקוה. mikveh. רבא אמר משום דהוי דבר שאינו
עושין ממנו מקוה. Rava amar mishum d'havi davar she'eino osin mimenu mikveh.
רבא Rava has his... your answer. I reject your assumption, says רבא
*Rava*. Who needs an official liquid to invalidate a מקוה *mikvah*? Liquid,
משקה mashka. *mashkeh*, maybe that's for squeezing on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, maybe
that's for טומאה וטהרה tumah vetaharah *Tumah ve-Taharah*, but to invalidate a
מקוה *mikvah* you do not need something to have a formal status
as a liquid. Okay, anything that you can't make a מקוה *mikvah*
out of invalidates the מקוה *mikvah*. וכל דבר שאין עושין הימנו מקוה
ופוסל את המקוה בשינוי מראה
*ve-chol davar she-ein osin heimenu mikvah u-posel es ha-mikvah be-shinnui mareh* and
therefore it'll invalidate it by changing the color even without the status
as a liquid. Okay, so that is the end of the first
part of this discussion. Discussion number one about squeezing fruits are which
types of fruit are דאורייתא d'Oraisa *de-Oraisa*, דרבנן *de-Rabbanan*, and מותר mutar
*muttar*. Olives and grapes are דאורייתא *de-Oraisa* and as you see from
this last discussion, not just because it's common but because it has
a formal status as a liquid as olive oil and grape juice.
Okay, things that are very rare are מותר *muttar* and everything in
the middle is דרבנן *de-Rabbanan*. What exactly we assume a very big
category of the דרבנן *de-Rabbanan*? In the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* it seems
to have been narrower, but anyway it's also much more common for
us to have fruit juices so we assume most almost most things
are at least דרבנן *de-Rabbanan*. Okay, that's in terms of and that's
in terms of allowing one to do it. In terms of benefiting
from the juice, that's the whole debate of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah*
and the חכמים *Chachamim*, can you benefit from the juice of the
middle category if it's set aside for food? We basically פוסקים *pasken*
you can, pretty much like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah*, important to know.
So if you're eating your grapefruit and you've got some juice that's
left behind, right? So there it was set aside לאכילה *le-achilah*, it
was the juice that came out, okay, so we פוסקים *pasken* like
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* you can drink that juice that came out.
Okay. Even if not grape juice, did I say grape? I meant
grapefruit. If you're eating your grapefruit. No, only in the middle category.
Are we supposed to do this just throw it out?
Yeah. Okay, now but now comes the third important הלכה *halacha* about
squeezing. It's actually quite well sort of organized here in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. The third important הלכה *halacha* is is squeezing into food,
squeezing onto your onto your onto your fish, into your salad, a
lemon. Is that okay? So let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל *Amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel*. אמר רב יהודה *Amar Rav
Yehudah* in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*. סוחט אדם אשכול של ענבים
לתוך הקדרה אבל Aval, לא לתוך הקערה *Socheit adam eshkol shel anavim
le-toch ha-kederah aval lo le-toch ha-kearah*. You can even take a אשכול
של ענבים *eshkol shel anavim* which we now said is דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*
and squeeze it into the קדרה *kederah* but not into into the
קערה *kearah*. Now why? The basic point is going to be that
when you squeeze it onto food it becomes itself like a status
like food and therefore you're not like separating liquid from food and
creating something new. It's just like you can take a slice out
of an apple, you can separate food from food. So if you
take if you squeeze it out and it becomes food when it
hits the thing, right, so it's not like you created something new,
it's just like you separated food from food and that actually is
allowed. Now here's very important question.
So what's קדרה *kederah* versus קערה *kearah*?
One is the collected and one's the individual? What's the difference between
קדרה *kederah* and קערה *kearah*?
No okay, okay, so I'm going to get to that. So let's
first talk about an extreme. One is I squeeze something onto my
fish, okay, or I squeeze something into my couscous. Okay, completely gets
absorbed by the food, so it's not like I made lemon juice,
it's like I just created food, okay, a new like it became
part of the food of the couscous and therefore creating food out
of food isn't a problem, it's only when I produce liquid.
So it doesn't have an independent existence
as liquid even though it was sort of liquid in air but
when it hits it doesn't. Now what constitutes turning it into food?
So I gave you an easy case which is it gets absorbed.
Or let's say I squeeze it onto a fish that doesn't have
the skin on it, it gets absorbed into the fish. But there
are cases that are less obvious. Let's say some gets absorbed into
the fish but a lot runs along the side. Or even another
case, let's say it gets squeezed onto salad, so it's there to
give taste to the food but it's sitting on top of the
salad, it's not absorbed. We actually rule although it's not even so
clear in the שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*, but למעשה lemaise *le-ma'aseh* we
rule that anything that is there to add taste to the food
is considered like part of the food. Even if its physical form
is a liquid, if it's there to add taste to food, not
liquid, squeezing into tea is you're making it part of liquid, so
that's problem. Squeezing onto a salad because it's giving taste to a
food is considered like part of the food. Not on chicken soup?
No, that yeah I know, but we could still consider that a
liquid. Okay, so so that actually is allowed. You can squeeze your
lemon onto your fish even if most of it will run off,
you can squeeze it onto your salad, it's there to give taste
to food, it's okay. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* when it says
here קדרה *kederah* could mean a pot with food in it. But
if you read רש"י *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* seems to be even more
extreme. רש"י *Rashi* seems to suggest that קדרה *kederah* is an empty
pot. But there's a difference. If I'm squeezing it into a plate,
right, into into a bowl, then if I'm squeezing it into a
bowl I want it to function like liquid, right, whereas if I
squeeze it into a pot, it's indicative of the fact that I'm
going to be making some food out of it. So even if
it's not immediately becoming part of food, even if just by the
context it's clear that that's the purpose that I'm doing it for,
that's enough to define it as food and not liquid. That's an
extreme position which we do not rule like. But it does sound
that way, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* contrasts קדרה *kederah* to קערה *kearah*,
pot versus plate, not food
versus. So we'll just make sure I understood that.
Yeah. Because like let's say I want to squeeze my lemon onto
the fish, right? Yeah. But you know, I mean it gets a
little bit annoying so like I put it in like a little
thing to pour on that.
אסור, asur? correct. According to the גמרא, Gemara. you might have been
able to do it, but למעשה we say no, only when it
goes straight into food.
Okay so let's just step here because what was the original source
for this that סחיטה s'chita is אסור? asur In the משנה, mishna,
it was a difference between if the if the original thing is
considered food or liquid. And now we're talking about that the thing
you're squeezing onto, right?
What do you mean if the original thing, what are you referring
to?
In the משנה, mishna, right?
Oh, if you set it aside לאוכלין le'ochlin or למשקין. lemashkin. Right.
No so in the משנה, mishna, right, right. Right. So that's a
good point, so in the משנה, mishna, the לאוכלין le'ochlin למשקין lemashkin
is whether is just the likelihood that you will come to squeeze
it. If you have things set aside because you're planning on squeezing,
we don't want you to benefit from the juices because then it's
very likely that you'll come to those things and squeeze them in
themselves. If they were set aside for eating, then even if some
juice happens to run off, we're not concerned that it'll lead you
to come to squeeze the thing. So there the difference of why
it was set aside was a difference about the likelihood that if
we let you drink the juices, you'll come to squeeze it. Here
the question is right, what the product is that actually is coming
out, whether it has a שם משקה. shem mashka. And as we
saw just recently from the discussion in the גמרא Gemara about olive
oil and grape juice, the idea of giving it a שם משקה
shem mashka is central to what makes this אסור דאורייתא. asur d'Oraisa.
So when it's serving food that undercuts the שם משקה shem mashka
even by ממש mamash grapes. By the way I should say that
even though the גמרא's Gemara example is by grapes, we're very מחמיר
machmir by grapes, so
technically although the גמרא Gemara you should be allowed to do it
even by food, squeeze an olive over your salad to make olive
oil, we tend to try to avoid grapes and olives, you know,
just because they're in the דאורייתא territory. But that's the גמרא. Gemara
But yes, it's a good question, but the difference there is that
that's a concern of will it lead to squeezing, here's the concern
about whether the product is actually considered a משקה. mashka.
Even if it leads to squeezing for some products it's not a
problem just squeezing it
onto your food anyway so it's not a problem.
Right, but though I should say but it reinforces because there when
you set aside let's say your your pomegranates למשקה lemashka it doesn't
mean you're drinking the pomegranates, it means that you're planning on producing
juice out of the pomegranates, so it's all pointing to the same
point that it's more problematic when what comes out of it is
defined as משקה. mashka. So when what comes out of it though
ends with food it's not defined as משקה. mashka? Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רב חסדא מדברי רבינו נלמד, Amar Rav Chisda midivrei Rabbeinu nilmad,
from the words of our Rabbi Shmuel we can learn,
חולב אדם עז לתוך הקדירה ולא לתוך הקערה, Cholev adam ez letoch
hakadera velo letoch hake'ara, that actually you can go and take your
goat over to a pot and milk your goat over the pot.
Again, we will assume it means there's food in the pot, it
might even mean without that. You can go ahead and milk your
goat over the pot but not straight into a dish because then
you are producing milk. Now I should say that תוספות Tosafot says
that this is only talking about יום טוב, Yom Tov, that he
believes that on שבת Shabbos, you cannot milk. Milking a cow is
different than squeezing a fruit. Why? Because it's an important conceptual point
because he says why is the reason that you're only חייב chayav
when you produce a משקה? mashka Essentially, I'm paraphrasing תוספות Tosafot a
little bit, essentially because משקה mashka. is qualitatively different than the food
which is אוכל. ochel. So if you produce אוכל ochel out of
your food, it's אוכל ochel and אוכל, ochel, you didn't do anything
new. Only when you produce משקה. mashka He says when you milk
a cow on שבת, Shabbos, the cow is not אוכל. ochel. You
can't eat the cow on שבת, Shabbos. you can't שחט shecht it,
you can't eat it. So therefore anything you produce, whether the milk
that comes out of it is considered משקה mashkeh. or אוכל, ochel,
it's qualitatively different than the cow which is inedible on שבת. Shabbos
So תוספות Tosafot says on שבת you would not be able to
even milk a cow even for אוכל. ochel. Okay, he wants to
limit it to יום טוב. Yom Tov. That's an interesting point. There's
a נפקא מינה nafka mina to this which is the case of
squeezing out fruit that is unripe and inedible. According to this position
of תוספות, Tosafot, but the juice you can use, according to this
position of תוספות, Tosafot, that's אסור even if you do it into
food because if the thing itself is inedible, then it doesn't matter
if what it produces is food or liquid, you'd be חייב. chayav.
Here the only reason it's מותר is because the thing you're starting
with is אוכל, ochel, so if you end with אוכל, ochel, you
haven't done anything of significance.
Okay, so for a טריפה treifa cow then it would be a
problem
according to presumably yeah.
Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. מיתיבי רמי בר
חמא, Meitivei Rami bar Chama, Rami bar Chama asked, עמוד, Amud, sixth
line, אבל, משקה הבא לאוכל אוכל הוא, mashka haba le'ochel ochel hu,
liquid that is going into food is considered food. Okay and again
the question here is הבא לאוכל haba le'ochel which means is it
intended for food or does it actually mean that it's gone entered
into food? Right, so that's the question of whether it's directly gone
into the food or not. מיתיבי רמי בר חמא. Meitivei Rami bar
Chama. By the way, I'll give you a flip case of where
it's intended which is an interesting מחלוקת. machlokes. Some people solve the
tea problem, how do you deal with the tea? So some people
just put the slice of lemon in the tea and let it
go by itself without squeezing. thing and that's fine. But there's a
common trick which is you take your spoon of sugar, you squeeze
it into the sugar and then it's into food and then you
mix it into the tea. So the חזון איש Chazon Ish says
I'm sorry that doesn't work because it's intended ultimately for the tea.
So that's sort of like this idea where is it intended, not
where it just goes immediately. But in our גמרא Gemara where it
could be that that's even לקולא, lekula, even if it's not directly
in food but intended for food. But again, we rule only when
it directly goes into food. Okay, so that's the idea. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מסי רמי בר חמא. masi Rami
bar Chama. So רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked: זב שחולב
את העז. zav shecholev et ha'ez. So now we're back to טומאה
tumah, וטהרה and מכשיר. machshir. If you have a זב zav that
is milking a goat. Now why specifically, well what does it mean?
It means because when you milk a זב zav makes something טמא
tamei not just by touching it but by moving it. So when
you milk, even if you don't touch the milk, you're causing it
to squirt, you're moving the milk. Okay, so החלב טמא. hachalav tamei.
It's טמא. tamei. Now ואמרת משקה בא לאוכלין אוכל הוא, ve'amrit mashkeh
ba le'ochlin ochel hu, if you say that if it's intended for
food, here really it's to mean intended since when do you milk
things into food? If it's intended for food it's food. So then
and we should assume maybe that this calls all cases of milking,
even when you're milking for food which maybe would mean to make
it into cheese I imagine or to mix it into some food,
not to drink it straight. So since it includes all types of
milking, so במאי אתכשר? bemai itkashar? So when it's being milked to
use the milk as food, how did it
become אתכשר, itkashar, it becomes susceptible? Because food, what does food need
to be susceptible for טומאה, tumah. to come in contact with a
liquid? So here you have an irony. Yeah, it's a liquid. You're
milking the milk, you're going to use it though with food or
maybe like cheese out of it. Even though it's physically liquid, it
has a halakhic status of אוכל. ochel. So now where did the
liquid that came in contact with it become טמא tamei by the
fact that the זב zav moved it? So do you see, so
okay, and assume that we're talking even of that type of milk,
milk going to be used for food. So the גמרא says: כדאמרי
דרבי יוחנן, kedamrei de'Rabbi Yochanan, like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says in
another case about a mother nursing her child and since she's טמא,
tamei, בטיפה מלוכלכת על פי הדד, betippa meluchlechet al pi hadad, which
there's a drop that sort of you know is at the is
on the nipple. So הכא נמי בטיפה מלוכלכת על פי הדד, hacha
nami betippa meluchlechet al pi hadad, here too, which means there's some
of the milk that's right on the you
know on the udder, the tit of the udder, which is not
going to be part of what you're going to eat. But it's
so and therefore that's משקה. mashkeh. Even though you presumably aren't going
to drink it either, but as long as you're not intending it
as food, it's enough to give it its status, its normal status,
its default status as משקה. mashkeh.
Bringing the rest of the milk that's a solid that's touching that
liquid.
Right, so because a little of the thing comes out, maybe when
you start milking you want to get some out just to whatever
get started or something like that and that's not intended to be
eaten, so that has its default status as משקה. mashkeh Everything else
after that that comes out touches it as a path through.
And then if it fell over
in the middle then it wouldn't be a problem? Yeah, I don't
know, that's the גמרא's answer. Okay, so מסי רבינא, masi Ravina, so
רבינא Ravina asked them this: טמא מת שסחט זיתים וענבים. temei met
sheshachat zeitim va'anavim. So now you've got somebody that's impure because they
touched a dead body so he's an אב הטומאה. avi hatumah. Okay,
and he is squeezing out זיתים וענבים, zeitim va'anavim, olives and grapes.
Now he only makes things טמא tamei through contact, not through moving
them. So let's take a look. So כביצה מכוונת. kebeitzah mechuvvenet. Now
let's say he's squeezing out exactly exactly the size of an egg.
So only stuff the size of an egg transfers טומאה. tumah It
could be טמא tamei even בכל שהוא, bekolshehu, this is רש"י'ס Rashi's
position and רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam argues but whatever, it's to come
טמא tamei בכל שהוא bekolshehu but only transfers טומאה tumah, if it's
the size of an egg. So you have an exact size of
an egg and you're squeezing. Now טהור, tahor, it's טהור. tahor. Why?
Because the actual grapes have not come in contact yet with liquid.
They don't become טמא tamei when I handle them. I squeeze out
a little bit of liquid. Okay, so that liquid comes out, so
now that liquid maybe touches the grapes and makes them ראוי raui
to be מקבל טומאה. mekabbel tumah. But now they are less than
a כביצה. kebeitzah. So they don't make the liquid coming out by
touching the liquid, they don't make the liquid טמא. tamei. Okay, so
I'm not touching the liquid, I'm only touching the grapes, the grapes
have not are not yet טמא tamei and therefore when they are
able to become טמא tamei they're less than a כביצה kebeitzah so
they can't make the liquid טמא. tamei. Okay. היותר מכביצה טמא. hayoter
mikebeitzah tamei. But if it's more than a כביצה kebeitzah then it
would be טמא. tamei. The liquid that came out would make them
a you know susceptible, they become טמא tamei and then they make
the liquid טמא. tamei. So ואמרת משקה בא לאוכלין אוכל
הוא, ve'amritat mashkeh ba le'ochlin ochel hu, if you say that משקה
that comes into food is food and presumably this is including the
cases where it's intended for food, right presumably it includes all cases.
So במאי אתכשר? bemai itkashar? So that liquid that come how did
these grapes become susceptible, the stuff that came out doesn't have a
status of liquid? So the גמרא says: הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק
לה. hu mosi vah u'mefarik lah. He asked it and he answered
it. בסוחט לתוך הקערה. besocheh letoch hake'arah. Finally, who says you have
to be talking that you're squeezing it into a pot? You're doing
it into a bowl. Okay fine, you're not talking about a case
that it's being done for food, you're talking about a classic case
that it's being done for liquid. All right, let's read one more.
אמר רבי ינאי כתנאי. Amar Rabbi Yannai kitannai. This issue, אמר רבי
ירמיה כתנאי. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah kitannai. This question... This question about whether
it's going to food, is it food or not, is like a
debate of תנאים. tanna'im. המולח בענבים, hamoile'ach ba'anavim,
if you smear the face of like of a bread with grape
juice, with like grapes, because you want it to give it a
shine when it cooks, when it bakes, you know, like we do
it like with an egg, right? לא הוכשר, lo huchshar, that does
not make it susceptible for טומאה, even though it's grape juice. רבי
יהודה אומר הוכשר, Rabi Yehuda omer huchshar, that does make it susceptible.
So why? Grape juice should make things susceptible. So מאי לאו בהא
קמיפלגי? mai lav beha kamifligi? This seems to be the debate. מר
סבר משקה על אוכל אוכל הוא, mar savar mashka al ochel ochel
hu, that it's here it's liquid that's going onto food, so is
it considered a liquid to make things susceptible? This seems to be
the exact debate. One says that it's food and therefore it doesn't
make it susceptible, ומר סבר לאו אוכל הוא, umar savar lav ochel
hu, it's not. אמר פפא, Amar Papa, no, דכולי עלמא משקה על
אוכל לאו אוכל הוא. dechulei alma mashka al ochel lav ochel hu.
Everybody would say it's not food, it's a liquid. So why wouldn't
it make the bread susceptible? והכא במשקה על איבוד קמיפלגי. vehacha bemashka
al ibud kamifligi.
Here it's because basically it's like it's being destroyed. You know, you
bake it, most of it evaporates, you're only left with a tiny
gleam. It's like the thing doesn't even really remain around, it's almost
like it's so so it's almost like it's being destroyed. So מר
סבר משקה, mar savar mashka, the other says I don't care, it
still is a liquid, right now it's a liquid, and so ומר
סבר לאו משקה, umar savar lav mashka, no, because it's being destroyed,
it's going to be mostly evaporated, it doesn't have its status. So
we'll continue with this. I know, because it's not really destroyed, you
want it there. But anyway, we'll continue with the גמרא isn't done
yet, we'll continue with that soon.